In this segment we ask whether we can
build block ciphers from simpler
本节 我们会提出一个问题 是否能使用简单基元 如伪随机数发生器来建造分组密码
primitives like pseudo random generators.
and we're gonna show the answer is yes. So to begin with, let's
而接下来我们会证明答案是肯定的 所以首先 我们会问
ask whether we can build pseudo random
functions as opposed to pseudo random
能否利用伪随机数发生器构建伪随机函数
permutations from a pseudo random
generator. Can we build a PRF from a PRG?
而不是伪随机置换。也就是我们能否由PRG构建PRF?
Our ultimate goal though is to build a
block cipher which is a PRP. And we'll get
尽管我们的最终目标是建造一个分组密码 也就是伪随机置换 最终我们会达到这个目标
to that at the end. Okay, for now we build
a PRF. So let's start with a PRG that
那现在 我们要构造一个伪随机函数 所以我们从可以将输入延长一倍的伪随机数产生器开始
doubles its inputs so the seeds for the
PRG is an element in K and the output is
所以伪随机数产生器的种子就是K里面的一个元素 输出为
actually two elements in K. So here we
have a schematic of the generator, that
K里面的两个元素 这里我们有一个发生器的原理图
basically takes his input of C and K, and
outputs two elements, in K as its output.
产生器得到C和K做为输入 然后输出K中的两个元素
And now what does it mean for this PRG
to be secure, recall this means that
伪随机数发生器是安全的指的是
essentially the output is
indistinguishable from a random element
不能从输出中区别出K^2里面的任意元素
inside of K squared Now it turns out that
it's very easy to define basically what's
事实上 依伪随机数产生器定义1位伪随机数函数是非常容易的
called a one bit PRF from this PRG. So
what's a one bit PRF is basically a PRF
所以1比特伪随机数函数指的是
who's domain is only one bit. Okay, so
it's a PRF that just takes one bit as
定义域仅为1比特的伪随机数函数 也就是只以一比特长度为输入
input. Okay, and the way we'll do it is
we'll say is if the input bit X is zero
所以 我们这里会说 如果输入位X是0
I'll put the left output and if the input
bit X is one then I'll put the right
那么我就会将PRF输出赋值为左边这个 如果输入位X是1 那我就会将PRF输出赋值为右边这个
output of the PRF. Okay, in symbols we
basically have what we wrote here. Now it
如果以符号表示的话 就是在这写的这个公式
is straightforward to show, that in fact G
is a secure PRG, then this one bit PRF is
可以很明显地看到 G就是一个安全的PRG 那么这个1比特PRF事实上就是
in fact a secure PRF. If you think about
it for a second, this is really a tautology.
一个安全PRF 如果你思考片刻就会知道 这完全是无谓的重复
Its really just stating the
same thing twice. So i will leave it for
将同样的事叙述两次 所以我会把这个留给你们
you to think about this briefly and see
and convince yourself that in fact this
去思考更简洁的叙述方式 并说服自己这个理论是正确的
theorem is true. The real questions is
whether we can build a PRF, that actually
真正要解决的问题是我们是否能建立一个PRF使之具有大于1比特的定义域
has a domain that is bigger than one bit.
Ideally we would like the domain to be 128
理想情况下 我们希望定义域为128比特
bits, just say as a AES has. So
the question is can we build 128 bit PRS
正如AES的域一样 那么问题就在于我们能否用一个伪随机数产生器来构建一个128位PRF？
from a pseudo random generator. Well so
let's see if we can make progress. So the
好了 让我们来看看我们能否取得进展
first thing we're gonna do is we're gonna
say, well again, let's start with a PRG
那么我们要做的第一件事是 以一个可以
that doubles its input let's see if we can
build a PRG that quadruples its inputs.
允许两倍输入的PRG开始 看我们是否能建一个能够接受四倍输入的PRG
Okay? So it goes from K to K to the fourth
instead of K to K squared. Okay, so let's
所以流程为从K→K^4 而不是K→K^2  好 让我们看看怎么完成这个过程
see how to do this. So here we start with
our original PRG that just doubles its
我们从能够两倍化输入的PRG开始
inputs, now remember that the fact that
this is a PRG means that the output of the
这里需要记住的是 这个是PRG 意味着它的输出和
PRG is indistinguishable from two random
values in K. Well, if the output looks
K中的两个随机值不可区分  如果输出与
like two random values in K, we can simply
apply the generator again to those two
K中的两随机值相似 那我们就可以将这两个输出再次送入PRG
outputs. So let's say we apply the
generator once to the left output, and
假设我们先把左边的输出送入PRG
once to the rights outputs. And we are
going to call the output of that, this
再把右边的这个输出送入PRG 然后我们称这
quadruple of elements, we are, are going
to call that G1K. And i wrote down in
四元组的输出为G1（K）这里我用符号表示这个
symbols what this generator does, but you
can see basically from this figure,
生成器的行为 但你能从这个图中看出
exactly how the generator works. So now
that we have a generator from K to K to
产生器的工作方式 所以我们有一个能做到K→K^4的产生器
the fourth, We actually get a two bit PRF.
Namely, what we will do is, we will say,
实质上也得到了一个2比特的PRF 换句话说 给定两比特
given two bits, 000110 or eleven, will
simply output the appropriate block that
00，01，10或11就可以输出与G1(K)输出对应的特定分组
the output of G1K. Okay, so now we can
basically have a PRF that takes four
所以 我们这里就有了一个可以
possible inputs as opposed to just two
possible inputs as before. So the question
接收四种输入的PRF 而不是像前面那样，只有两种可能输入的PRF了
you should be asking me is why is this G1
case secure? Why is it a secure PRG? That
那么问题是为什么G1是安全的？ 为什么G1是个安全的PRG？
is why is this quadruple of outputs
indistinguishable from random. And so
为什么这个四元组输出与随机序列不可被区分？
let's do a quick proof of this, we'll just
do a simple proof by pictures. So here's
让我们仅仅以图片形式快速证明这些问题
our generator that we want to prove is
secure. And what that means is that we
这个是我们想证明是安全的产生器 我们试图证明其安全性
want to argue that this distribution is
indistinguishable from a random four-tuple
这意味着我们想证明这个分布与K^4中的随机四元组是不可区分的
in K to the fourth. Okay so our goal is to
prove that these two are
所以我们的目标是证明这两个
indistinguishable. Well let's do it one
step at a time. We know that the generator
是不可区分的 我们一步一步来 我们知道这个产生器
is a secure generator, therefore in fact
the output of the first level is
是安全的 因此 第一层的输出
indistinguishable from random. In other
words, if we replace the first level by
与随机数是不可区分的 换句话说 如果我们以真随机串替换第一层
truly random strings these two are truly
random picked in the key space, then no
这两个是从密钥空间中选出的真随机串
efficient adversary should be able to
distinguish these two distributions. In
那么没有有效的攻击能够区分这两个分布 事实上
fact, if you could distinguish these two
distributions, it's easy to show that you
如果你可以区分这两个分布 那很容易证明
would break the original PRG. Okay, but
essentially you see that the reason we can
你也可以破解最初的PRG 你应该知道我们能进行替换
do this replacement, we can replace the
output of G, with truly random values, is
（以真随机值替换G的输出）的原因是
exactly because of the definition of the
PRG, which says the out put of the PRG is
PRG的定义 即PRG的输出与随机数是不可区分的
indistinguishable from random, so we might
as well just put random there, and no
所以 我们同样可以将随机数放到这里 并且
efficient adversary can distinguish the
resulting two distributions. Okay, so far
没有有效的攻击可以分辩出这两个分布 目前为止一切还算顺利
so good, but now we can do the same thing
again to the left hand side. In other
现在我们给左边做同样的处理 换句话说
words, we can replace these two pseudo
random outputs, by truly random outputs.
我们以真随机输出替换这两个伪随机输出
And again because the generator G is
secure, no efficient adversary can tell
同样地 由于发生器G是安全的 所以没有有效的攻击可以辨别出
the difference between these two
distributions. But differently, if an
这两种分配方式的区别 但不同的是
adversary can distinguish these two
distributions, then we would also give an
如果一个攻击者可以分辨这两种分配方式的不同 那我们也可以给出
attack on the generator G. And now finally
we're gonna do this one last time. We're
一个对发生器G的攻击 最后我们再做一次替换
gonna replace this pseudo random pair By a
truly random pair, and lo and behold we
我们以真随机对替换掉这一伪随机对 你看！
get the actual distribution that we were
shooting for, we would get a distribution
我们获得了我们想要的分布 也就是以
that is really made of four independent
blocks. And so now we have proved this
四个独立分组构成的分布 我们已经证明在这个转换中
transition basically that these two
indistinguishable, these two
这两个是无法区分的  这两个
indistinguishable, and these two
indistinguishable, and therefore these two
是无法区分的 还有这两个是不可区分的 因此 这两个
are indistinguishable, which is what we
wanted to prove. Okay so this is kind of
也是无法区分的 这正是我们想证明的 这是证明的
the high level idea for the proof, it is
not too difficult to make this rigorous,
大致想法 要想用其它方法严谨地证明并非难事
but i just wanted to show you kinda
intuition for how the proof works. Well,
但我只想告诉大家直观的证明思路
if we were able to extend the generators
outputs once, there's nothing preventing
如果我们可以延长发生器输出一次 那就没有什么能阻止
us from doing it again so here is a
generator G1 that outputs four elements in
我们再延长一次 于是这里有一个输出密钥空间中四个元素的发生器G1
the key space. And remember the output
here is indistinguishable from our random
并且记住 这里的输出与随机四元组是不可区分的
four-tuple, that's what we just proved.
And so there's nothing preventing us from
就是我们刚证明过的 我们完全可以再次用这个发生器延长输出
applying the generator again. So we'll
take the generator apply it to this random
这里我们用这个发生器来延长这个看似随机的串
looking thing and we should be able to get
this random looking thing. This pair over
当然得到的也是一个看似随机的串 就是这一对
here that's random looking. And we can do
the same thing again, and again, and
我们当然能一次又一次地延长输出
again. And now basically we've built a new
generator that outputs elements in K to
所以基本上 我们建立了一个可以输出K^8中元素的发生器
the eighth, as opposed to K to the fourth.
And again the proof of security is very
与前面的K^4发生器不同 还有 其安全性证明与
much the same as the one I just showed you
essentially you gradually change the
我前面展示的方法一样 也就是那个以真随机输出替换原输出的方法
outputs into truly random outputs. So we
would change this to a truly random
所以我们会先将这个替换为真随机输出
output, then this, then that, then this,
then that and so on and so forth. Until
然后这里、接着那里、然后这里、再接着那里等等 直到
finally we get something that's truly
random and therefore the original two
最后我们得到真正的随机字符串 并且以G2(K)开始的两个原始分配
distributions we started with G2K and
truly random are indistinguishable. Okay,
与真随机数是不可区分的
so far so good. So now we have a generator
that outputs elements in K to the eighth.
到目前还好 所以我们得到了一个能输出K^8中元素的发生器
Now if we do that basically we get a three
bit PRF. In other words, at zero, zero,
基本上就是一个3比特PRF 换句话说
zero this PRF would output this block, and
so on and so forth until one, one, one it
在000时 我们输出这个分组 以此类推 直到111时
would output this block. Now the
interesting thing is that in fact this PRF
它会输出这个分组 现在，有趣的是事实上这个PRF很容易计算
is easy to compute. For example, suppose
we wanted to compute the PRF at the point
例如 如果我们想要计算PRF
one zero one. Okay, it's a three bit PRF.
Okay so one zero one. How would we do
在101时的输出 注意这个是3比特PRF 所以选101 接下来呢？
that? Well basically we would start from
the original key K. And now we would apply
我们先以原始密钥K开始 然后我们会使用发生器G
the generator G but we would only pay
attention to the right output of G,
但我们只关注G输出的右侧
because the first bit is one. And then we
will apply the generator again, but we
因为第一个比特是1 接下来 我们再使用发生器一次 但
would only pay attention to the left of
the output of the generator because the
我们只关注左边的输出 因为
second bit is zero. And then we would
apply the generator again and only pay
第二个比特是0 再之后 我们再用一次发生器 并且只关注
attention to the right outputs because the
third bit is one and that would be the
右侧的输出 因为第三个比特是1 然后这个输出就是
final output. Right, so you can see that,
that lead us to 101, and in fact because
最终输出 就像你看到的 这个就是101的情况 事实上
the entire generator is pseudo
random, we know that, in particular that,
因为整个发生器是伪随机的 所以我们可以知道
this output here is pseudo random. Okay,
so this gives us a three bit PRF. Well, if
这个输出也是伪随机的 这就给了我们一个3比特的PRF
it worked three times, there's no reason
why it can't work N times. And so if we
好了 既然这个过程能生效三次 那没就有理由不能生效N次 如果我们
apply this transformation again and again,
we arrive at what's called a GGMPRF. Ggm
一次又一次地运用这种转换 最终我们就会得到一个GGMPRF
stands for Goldreich, Goldwasser and
Micali these are the inventors of
GGM是指Goldreich、Goldwasser、Micali 他们是这个PRF的发明家
this PRF and the way it works is as
follows. So we start off with a generator
这个PRF的工作方式是这样的 我们以一个两倍化输出的发生器开始
just doubles its outputs, and now we're
able to build a PRF that acts on a large
之后我们能够建一个拥有巨大定义域的PRF
domain mainly a domain of size zero one to
the N. Or N could be as big as 128 or even
这个域的大小为0 1一直到N 这里N可以是128甚至更大
more. So let's see, suppose we're given an
input in 01 to the N, let me show you how
让我们来看看 假设给定一个长为N的0、1比特输入 我会展示给你们怎么
to evaluate the PRF. Well by now you
should actually have a good idea for how
求这个PRF 当然你现在应该也有一个应该怎么做的想法
to do it. Essentially we start from the
original key and then we apply the
基本上 我们以原始密钥开始 然后使用
generator and we take either the left or
the right side depending on the bit X0 and
发生器并且以X0的比特来决定来选择左、右的输出
then we arrive at the next key, K1. And
then we apply the generator again and we
之后我们得到了下一密钥K1 然后我们继续使用发生器
take the left or the right side depending
on X1 and we arrive at the next key. And
并以X1的值决定输出是左边还是右边 这步我们得到下一个密钥
then we do this again and again, until
finally we are arrive at the output. So we
然后我们循环做这个步骤 直到我们得到最后的输出
have processed all end bits, and we arrive
at the output of this function. And
这样我们就处理了所有的比特 并且得到了整个函数的输出
basically we can prove security again
pretty much along the same lines as we did
而且我们可以用前面证明的方法来证明整个过程的安全性
before, and we can show that if G is a
secure PRG, then in fact we get a secure
这样我们就能知道 如果G是一个安全的PRG 那么事实上 我们就得到了一个安全的PRF
PRF, on 01 to the N, on a very large
domain. So that's fantastic. Now we have
它定义在^N上且具有很大的定义域 整个过程很奇炒
we have essential, we have a PRF that's
provably secure, assuming that the
本质上 我们就有了一个可证其安全的PRF
underlying generator is secure, and the
generator is supposedly much easier to
以安全的发生器为前提 并且整个发生器（=PRF）
build than an actual PRF. And in fact it
works on blocks that can be very large, in
比一个实际的PRF更容易建造 它还可以处理非常大的分组
particular, 01 to the 128th, which is what
we needed. So you might ask well why isn't
特别地 如128位的01比特串 这正是我们需要的 所以你可能会问到
this thing being used in practice? And the
reason is, that it's actually fairly slow.
为什么不在实际中应用这个东西呢？原因是 它的速度很慢
So imagine we plug in as a generator we
plug in the salsa generator. So now to
想象现在我们接通一个发生器 一个salsa发生器
evaluate this PRF at a 128 bit inputs, we
would basically have to run the salsa
现在来计算这个PRF在某个128位输入的值 我们必须要运行这个salsa发生器
generator 128 times. One time per bit of
the input. But then we would get a PRF
128次 一次只对应一位输入 这样我们会得到一个
that's 128 times slower than the original
salsa. And that's much, much, much slower
PRF 其运行时间却是原本Salsa的128倍 这比AES慢太多太多
than AES. Aes is a heuristic PRF. But
nevertheless it's much faster then what we
AES是一种启发式PRF 但不管怎么样 它比我们刚做出来的这个要快得多
just got here. And so even though this is
a very elegant construction, it's not used
所以即使它的结构非常简洁 我们依然不会用
in practice to build pseudo random
functions although in a week we will be
它来建造伪随机函数 虽然本周我们会
using this type of construction to build a
message integrity mechanism. So the last
用这种结构来构建数据完整性的机制 最后
step, is basically now that we've built a
PRF, the questions is whether we can
我们已经建了一个PRF 但问题是 我们是否能够
actually build the block cypher. In other
words, can we actually build a secure PRP
构建分组密码 换句话说 我们能否从一个安全的PRG构建一个安全的PRP？
from a secure PRG. Everything we've done
so far is not reversible. Again if you
迄今我们所做的一切并不是可逆的
look at this construction here, we can't
decrypt basically given the final outputs.
如果你们看着这个结构 只给定最后输出 并不能解密出明文
It is not possible to go back or at least
we don't know how to go back the, the
你不能逆向返回 或者至少 我们不知道怎么逆向返回出原明文
original inputs. So now the question of
interest is so can we actually solve the
一个比较有趣的问题是我们能不能解决
problem we wanted solve initially? Mainly,
can we actually build a block cipher from
我们最初想要解决的那个问题 也就是 我们能不能根据安全的PRG构建一个分组密码？
a secure PRG? So ill let you think about
this for a second, and mark the answer. So
我会留点时间让你们考虑 并记下答案
of course I hope everyone said the answer
is yes and you already have all the
当然我希望每个人的回答都是肯定的 并且你已经想出
ingredients to do it. In particular, you
already know how to build a PRF from a
完成它所需要的材料 更具体点 你已经知道怎么从一个伪随机数发生器来构建一个PRF
pseudo random generator. And we said that
once we have a PRF we can plug it into the
我们以前说过 只要你有一个PRF 那么我们就可以将它嵌入
Luby-Rackoff construction, which if you
remember, is just a three-round feistel.
Luby-Rackoff结构 如果你记得 它只是一个三轮Feistel网络
So we said that if you plug a secure PRF
into a three-round feistel, you get a
所以 我们说过 如果你将一个安全PRF嵌入到一个三轮Feistel中 你会得到
secure PRP. So combining these two
together, basically gives us a secure PRP
安全的PRP 所以结合这两点 基本上就能够由PRG生成一个安全的PRP
from a pseudo random generator. And this
is provably secure as long as the
这个PRP的安全条件是 只需要
underlying generator is secure. So it's a
beautiful result but unfortunately again
结构中内含的发生器是安全的 这个是很好的结果 但不幸的是
it's not used in practice because it's
considerably slower than heuristics
实际应用中不会出现这种用法 因为这种结构比类似AES的启发式结构来的慢得多
constructions like AES. Okay so
this completes our module on constructing
好了 这样我们就完成了构建过程
pseudo random permutations, and pseudo
random functions. And then in the next
伪随机置换和函数 在接下来的模块中
module we're gonna talk about how to use
these things to do proper encryption.
我们将讨论怎么运用这些东西来正确地加密